I hope everyone is staying dry. I'm not.
So as I mentioned last time, the Marin project had a 1e23 FLOPs
which was running, and it finished.
And it actually matched the forecast.
So remember we were running this.
Each of these curves is essentially
IsoFLOPs curve, which is a bunch of smaller model runs.
And you try to find the compute optimal point.
You fit a scaling law.
And this was the point where we predicted the loss,
and we ran the model and it got loss within 0.05.
So I thought that was pretty cool.
And if you extrapolate out to GPT-5 level performance,
this is the loss you get.
Of course, your mileage might vary depending
on how these scaling loss are.
OK, I just wanted to share that news.
So last lecture I gave an overview of the entire class.
And we are talking about tokenization,
which is going to be on the first assignment.
Today, I want to talk about resource accounting, which
is going to be more on the systems side of things.
So to recall, the main thing we're trying to do
is train the best model we can given a finite set of resources,
which could be compute, memory, sometimes data.
But that's not really going to be a limiting factor for us
in this class. And our goal is to simply maximize
the computational efficiency of our training.
So before you can optimize the computational efficiency,
we need to understand the efficiency of a given computation.
And for that, we need to understand the compute
and memory characteristics.
Just to give you a taste of the type of questions
you will hopefully be able to answer by the end of the class,
so here's a question.
How long would it take to train a 70 billion
parameter model on 15 trillion tokens on 1024--
actually, this should be H100. So how do you answer that?
Well, there's a formula, which we'll
talk about how you can get the number of FLOPs
to be 6 times the number of parameters
times the number of tokens.
We can look up the spec sheet to see how fast the H100 is.
We have this thing called MFU, which we'll talk about 0.5.
Then you can estimate the number of FLOPs
that you need that the hardware gives you per day.
And then you can compute the number of days.
So the number of days is 143. Here's another question.
What's the largest model you can train on H100s using AdamW?
So you can look at, well, H100s have 80 gigabytes of each VM
memory, the number of bytes per parameter, which is 2 plus 2
plus 4 plus 4. We'll explain where that comes from.
And then the number of parameters
is that you can get is going to be about 53 billion.
So there's some caveats here that we
don't count the activations which
depends on batch size and the sequence length.
So this is all very rough back-of-the-envelope calculations.
But hopefully by the end of this class
you'll understand where these come from.
And the point is not to precisely calculate
every single thing, but just get the rough shape of things.
OK. So last time I talked about knowledge and what you
can take away from this class--
mechanics, which are how things work.
So today, that would be pretty straightforward.
The mechanics are just how PyTorch works, how tensors work.
It should be fairly--there's no magic here.
The mindset I want to impart on you
is that resource accounting is going to be very crucial.
And I want everyone to get in the habit
whenever you write this line of code,
think about the performance characteristics.
And then finally intuitions.
Here we're just going to get a sense of the resources, how
they're spent. There's going to be no ML magic today.
I'll leave that to Tatsu for the next lecture. OK.
So let's get into things.
So let's start bottom up and start building up.
So what is at the bottom? At the bottom are tensors.
So tensor 是存储一切的基本单元。
如果你有参数、梯度、优化器状态，
数据、激活，本质上一切都是 tensor。
比如，你可以看看 DeepSeek 3.2 模型。
你会看到模型本身是
一堆不同的 tensor。
每个 tensor 都有一些形状，还有
一些精度，我稍后会讲。
所以如你所知，tensor 包含了向量、
矩阵，并且可以推广到任意数量的实体。OK。
那我们来谈谈存储 tensor 需要多少开销。
这取决于 tensor 的类型。
一般来说，我们会处理那些
存储浮点数的 tensor，但 tensor 也可以
存储整数和其他类型。
对于浮点数，通常当你说到 float，
我认为人们默认指的是 float，
也就是所谓的 float32。
所以一个 float32，如果拆开来看，有 32 位。
其中一位是符号位，8 位
是指数，提供了动态范围。
剩下的就是尾数或小数部分，
提供了精度变化。
这也称为 fp32 或单精度。
单精度这个词来源于
早期做科学计算的时候，
float32 就像是基准线。
就像如果有人给你一个
float，你会期望它至少是单精度。
如果你想要更高的精度，那么你
可以用双精度，也就是 float64。
但在深度学习中，我们走的是另一个方向，
因为即使 32 位也很多了。
我们想做的那些计算
并不需要像某些
数值模拟那样高的精度。OK。
所以在讲其他类型之前，我们先看看 float32。
那我们构造一个 4 乘 8 的矩阵。
默认情况下，你创建的 tensor 类型是 float32。
所以如果你想要别的类型，你需要声明它。
And the memory usage is just the number of elements times
the element size here, which is 4 bytes for a 32-bit number.
And that's going to be 128 bytes.
So just to give you a kind of perspective,
so in GPT-3, which is a fairly old model
one of the matrix in the feedforward layer
is about 2.3 gigabytes. So these tensors can get quite big.
And this is not even the biggest one that one can imagine.
OK. So since we're interested in efficiency,
we want to generally reduce the amount of storage.
And we'll see that as you reduce the precision,
you actually save memory.
And you also save time because operating on 16 bits
is going to be faster, let's say, twice
as fast, but not always. It depends.
And then memory, by reducing memory,
we'll see later that actually reducing memory
can save time as well, which is maybe less obvious.
But it will hopefully become clear.
So the obvious thing is you say, OK,
let's take away half the bits. Now you have float16.
So float16 says you have a sign.
You have only 5 bits of exponent,
and then the rest is the mantissa.
So float16 is good, except for its dynamic range is poor.
So even if you have, let's say, try to construct 1e minus 8
tensor, then that is actually just 0.
So you can't really represent very big numbers,
and you can't represent very small numbers.
And the reason is that this exponent
it's only 5 bits of exponent compared to 8.
So if you train with fp16, which people did back in the day,
you will get instability. You will get underflow.
You get overflow. You'll get NaNs. It's pretty challenging.
So bfloat16 was invented.
So this was developed in actually 2018 to address this issue.
And the observation was that well, let's not compromise
on the number of bits.
The number of bits is going to be the same as fp16.
But we're going to shift some of the bits from the mantissa
to the exponent.
So that means it has more dynamic range than float16.
And it actually has the same dynamic range as float32.
But of course, the resolution is worse
because there's no free lunch here.
But it turns out that in a lot of deep learning applications,
this is well worth the trade-off.
You want the dynamic range to not overflow and underflow.
And because things are kind of sloppy and stochastic anyway,
you don't need that much resolution.
So let me actually skip over this part.So OK.
So to summarize, what are the implications for training?
So you can absolutely train with float32.
And if you're training a small model,
you probably just-- and you don't want to worry about it,
just float32 is fine.But it requires 4 bytes of--
sorry, 4 bytes of memory per float.
And that can take up a lot of memory.
And if you train with float16, then that's
going to be too risky.So bf16 is the sweet spot.
Even bf16 can be risky as well.
Maybe [INAUDIBLE] a little bit.One thing that people have--
has become common practice is to use mixed precision training.
And the actually let me--
OK, let me compile this again.I think these are stale.
So mixed precision training is where some of the computations
use some precision, and for other computations
use other precision.So in general, as a general rule,
bf16 is what you would use for parameters, activations,
and gradients.And for optimizer states, you would use fp32.
And we'll discuss a little bit more about that later.
And to do invoke mixed precision training,
so PyTorch has an AMP library.
We're not going to talk too much about this,
but you basically wrap your code,
and PyTorch has-- the library takes care of it
automatically for you in the sense
that it tries to cast things into a bf16 when it's safe.
So, for example, MatMuls are generally safe.
But if you try to do exponentiation,
then it will try to leave things as fp32. OK.
So we could do bf16, I think is probably
where this class will end.
But if you're feeling very adventurous, you can go farther.
So fp8, this was introduced four years ago.
It actually has been standardized.
So if you look at fp8, there's actually two versions
because depending on if you need more dynamic range or more
resolution. And there's two versions of them.
And so we're not going to talk about that.
But NVIDIA has some--the transformer engine supports fp8.
And most recently, you can actually go down to fp4.
So last year, NVIDIA developed nvfp4,
and there's only 4 bits per value.
So if you just to-- so we're on the same page.
4 bits is not a lot.
I can write all the values down on a single line here
between minus 6 and 6. So that's not very much precision.
Now there's a little bit of a cheat here.
Because if you just naively only use these values,
you're not going to be able to train very well.
So what actually this means is that every value
you can have this 4 bits of freedom, but there are blocks.
And each block can be scaled up and down accordingly.
So you can actually represent more values
but you can't represent the full dynamic range
for every single value.
And there is a model released actually this year,
the Nemotron 3 Super, which was trained in fp4,
which I think is pretty cool. OK.
So some of this it's just good to know.
And some of this you can't even touch.
It's not like you create a tensor
and you call it fp-- you can make it fp4.
A lot of this is done under the hood by NVIDIA's software stack.
OK. This was a bit of a long digression,
but it's maybe helpful to appreciate
that the intricacies of precision here.
Any questions before I move on? Yeah. Sorry.
It was a question like, when you have a block,
你正在按那个 block 缩放 tensor 中所有相同的东西。
所以所有这些的比值仍然会处于 fp4 中。是的。
所以问题是，只是——
[INAUDIBLE] 最大值是为了有更高的精度。
是的，所以问题是，好，只是
再解释一下 block。
所以你有，比如说一个 block。
在那个 block 内，你可以在 4 位范围内变化。
此外，所有这些值
都可以根据你的缩放因子有多少位
进行放大和缩小。
所以如果你看单个值，
你实际上能得到超过 4 位的动态范围。
但这就像是你不能让
这个值在这边很高，而相邻的值
在这边很低。
一个问题是，那 1 位呢 [INAUDIBLE] 影响 1 位
[INAUDIBLE]？是的，所以显然有很多训练。
所以也许这是个好时机。
所以问题是关于 1 位的，因为你不能真的
比那更低。
所以训练和推理之间是有区别的。
所以很多低位的东西，如果我们谈到——
我想我们稍后会谈到量化，
是你在也许甚至 bf16 上训练一个模型。
然后你量化到，比如说，1 位或 2 位。
那比训练一个 1 位语言模型容易得多，
我认为没人做过。
也许可能，但我不认为
有人训练过任何可信的东西。好。
那我们继续吧。所以我们谈到了 tensor。
内存计算相当简单，
就是元素数量乘以
每个元素占用多少内存。
所以默认情况下，你在 PyTorch 中创建的 tensor
会在 CPU 上。
当然，你必须——如果你想让事情变快，
你想把它们移到 GPU 上。
实际上，所以有一点——
我对幻灯片有一个小问题
that they were executed on my laptop, which
means that I don't have GPU.
So some of the code I'll just show but not execute.
OK. Let's see. This is maybe not that interesting,
but I think everyone knows how to move tensors to GPU.
But just remember to do that.
Otherwise you won't get your speed-ups.
OK, so we talked about memory of tensors,
which is very straightforward.
Now let's talk about computing with tensors.
So before talking about FLOPs accounting
for the tensor operations, let's take
a little bit of a digression to talk about einops.
So how many of you are familiar used einops before? OK.
So maybe 2/3. OK. Good.
So the motivation behind einops, for those of you
who might not be indoctrinated is, it's very easy to mess up.
Or I find it very confusing to look at code such as this.
And you have x and y.
And then you have transpose minus 2 and minus 1.
And you're trying to figure out what minus 2 and minus 1 is.
And so this is maybe the motivation
for using variable and names rather than indices.
So einops is a library for manipulating tensors
where the dimensions are named.
And this is inspired by Einstein summation notation.
There's a nice tutorial which you can go through.
I'm just going to cover some of the basics.
So basically, the way to think about einsum
is a generalized matrix multiplication with good bookkeeping.
So here's an example. So I have a matrix 3 by 4.
I have a 4 by 3 matrix.
And if I do the MatMul, this is actually pretty nice.
It's pretty easy to understand.
In einops, basically you say x has two dimensions, the row
and the column, which I'm going to name seq1 and hidden.
I'm going to have y.
That's a matrix which has also rows and columns, which I'm
going to name hidden and seq2.
And I'm going to produce tensor or here
a matrix, where the dimensions are indexed by seq1 and seq2.
And anything that is not mentioned here,
the hidden gets summed out.
So the way this works is I'm going to sum over--
enumerate over all possible values of all the variables
that occur here, which are seq1's hidden and seq2.
And I'm going to basically index into x, index into y,
multiply them and dump them, accumulate them
into the result z sub seq1 and seq2.
All right. So you say this is--come on.
This is much easier than this, right?
OK, let's try a more complicated example.
So here's the example I showed before. Now we have a tensor.
It's 2 by 3 by 4, another tensor 2 by 3 by 4.
And if I were doing things the old way, basically what
I'm doing is transposing these last two.
And then because at implicitly batches
the dimensions that are not the MatMul dimensions, then
you get the answer. So you have to reason about this a bit.
Einops makes this very clear.
It says there's a batch dimension.
There's seq1 hidden, seq2 hidden.
And I'm just going to produce batch seq1 and seq2.
And notice that there's no transpose because I just--
in some sense I've done the transpose by the naming.
If I had hidden and seq2, then it would be no transpose.
I always get confused by transposes.
And the fact I don't have to think about transposing it
makes me happy. OK.
So if you want to get fancy, you can say, well, batch--
I'm just going to replace with dot, dot, dot.
And this means that if I had, let's say, rank
10 tensor with eight different batching dimensions,
I can just write dot dot, dot without enumerating all of them.
And this comes up in language modeling
because you might have a batch dimension.
You might have a sequence dimension.
You might have a head dimension.
And you're trying to do this matrix operation
for all of them.
And you might not want to have to just worry about this.
And the nice thing is that you can write modular code where
you can write this dot, dot, dot without worrying
about even the shape of the tensor that comes in.
All right. So that's einsum which is in the einops library.
There's a reduce.
So this is a generalization of sum, mean, max, and min.
So for example, if you have, let's say, this tensor
and you want to sum according to dimension of dim minus 1,
which means sum along the last dimension here.
So again, I don't like this notation.
But what you can do is call reduce.
And basically what you say is that there's
some batching dimensions.
In this case, it would be these first two.
And then there's some hidden dimension
which doesn't appear on the right side, which
means that it gets summed.
And here, I put sum, which means that the aggregation reduction
operation is sum.
But you can replace it with mean or max or min. Yeah.
Is there some speed-up to this?
This basically reduces to the same type
of primitive operations.
You can think about it as just sugar.
So it should be the same.
OK. So the final thing I'll talk about is rearrange.
So this is, I think, a pretty powerful tool.
I think it will come up in an assignment once.
So sometimes you have a dimension
that actually represents two dimensions,
and you want to operate on one of them.
And the reason this happens is that sometimes you have a matrix
and you flatten it.
And then you want to maybe unflatten and flatten.
So this is the way that it works here.
So imagine I have a matrix 3 by 8
but where this dimension, 8 actually represents a 2
by 4 matrix.
So I want to multiply that 2 by 4 matrix by this 4 by 4 matrix.
所以我接下来要做的，实际上是调用rearrange。
而我在这里做的是说，看，
这是一些批次维度，
这里它对应的就是这里的第一个元素。
然后在这里，我用括号表示这个h实际上
代表heads和hidden1的乘积，
这里我必须——显然有多种方式
来分解它。可以是2乘4，4乘2。
所以我说heads的数量是2，
这意味着hidden1是4。
然后我可以把它拆成两个维度，heads
和hidden。好。这样就创建了这个。
所以之前x看起来像这样，现在x看起来像这样。
所以我想这可能有点难看清。
然后你可以对w执行你的操作变换。
这就是我们之前见过的，
你有一个标准的MatMul，
这里x有一些批次维度。
这是hidden乘以hidden2。
然后一旦你完成了这个变换，
你就可以rearrange回来。这很直接。
你基本上是看两个维度，
然后你可以把它们组合成一个维度。
是的。你能把一个二维的东西
塑造成一维的吗，不是有两种方式吗？
比如，你可以按行主序或列主序来做？
是的，所以问题是如果你有一个一维的东西
然后你把它变成——抱歉，你有一个二维的东西
然后你把它变成一维的东西，
你用哪种方式做？
嗯，你做的顺序是由这里的顺序指定的。好。
是的。
所以有时我觉得需要一点时间来适应，
但这很值得，因为一旦你有了einsum，
你就会以不同的方式思考。
所有的转置和归约，所有这些，它只是
它变得更流畅。
你必须更深入地思考这些更定制的原语。
好的。好。我们要用einops。
我们稍后会看到一点。
那么现在我们回到资源核算的问题。
我有一些张量。
我们已经讨论过它们如何占用内存。
那么它们消耗多少计算量呢？
我们用来衡量计算成本的标准
是FLOPs的数量。一个FLOP是一次浮点运算。
我们假设它是一次基本运算，比如加法
或乘法。
当然，GPU还能做其他事情。
但大多数情况下，我们只是
忽略它们，因为这些才是基础，
会占用你大部分时间。
让我很在意的一点是，如果我说FLOPs这个词，
它实际上是有歧义的。
有FLOPs，指的是
浮点运算的数量，
通常写作FLOPs，小写s。
这是已完成的计算量的度量。
然后还有FLOP/s，即每秒浮点运算
次数。
有时候也很容易混淆地写成FLOPS
大写S，但我会一直写/s
来明确这是在衡量硬件的速度。
所以如果你看到H100有800、989万亿次浮点运算，
那是第二种。
而当我说GPT-3用了325或者其他数字的FLOPs时，
那是第一种。先把这一点说清楚。
先给大家一个数量级的概念。
所以当我说1e22或23或25的FLOPs时，
这些隐式地指的是计算量
或者某些模型的规模。
所以如果你看H100——
如果你看这份光鲜的规格表——
其实不在这页上。算了。
有一份规格表，我会告诉你
对于bf16，FLOP/s的数量是1979。
然后你去实际测试一下，
你会发现等等，那并不是
我实际得到的结果。然后你去读细则。
有一个脚注说这是在稀疏性条件下的结果。
所以稀疏矩阵和稠密矩阵都是 2。
所以你总是要把这些数字除以 2。
所以这就是为什么你看到这些除以 2。好的。
所以这让我们可以——
只是为了直观理解，假设你有 8 块 H100
所以这里有一个节点运行两周。
那就是 8 乘以两周内的秒数。
其实，这看起来是一周。好的，没问题。
它是一周乘以你每秒获得的 FLOPs 数。
所以大约是 5e21。好的。
所以这只是为了建立直观理解
关于某些类型硬件的 FLOPs 数
以及某些类型模型需要多少 FLOPs。
这没什么复杂的。只是数学和粗略估算。好的。
所以现在让我们做一些更机械的事情。
所以假设你有一个线性模型。
事实证明，很多计算 FLOPs 的方法
实际上核心就是线性矩阵乘法。
所以这其实并没有太大的通用性损失。
所以你有 n 个点。每个点是 d 维的。
我们将把每个 d 维向量
映射到一个 k 维输出。
所以 B 是点的数量。
D 是维度数，输入维度，
K 是输出维度。好的。
所以让我们构造一些 x，即数据矩阵
B 乘 D。权重矩阵是 D 乘 K。
当你做矩阵乘法时，问题是这有多少
FLOPs。事实证明这
基本上是三个维度的乘积的 2 倍。
理解这一点的方式是我们
对每个三元组有一次乘法，然后还有一次
加法。所以有一个减 1，因为如果你
不必实际相加，就像这种情况下 D 减 1 次。
但让我们忽略这一点。好的。我会回到这个问题。
如果这有点快，我想还有
另一种推导方法。
那么其他操作的 FLOPs 呢？
所以逐元素操作就是矩阵的大小。
我想这相当清楚。
So addition also requires m n FLOPs.
So in general, no other operation
you'll encounter as expensive as matrix multiplication
for large enough matrices.
So in general, we're just going to focus
on what MatMuls are doing, with important caveat of when
we talk about memory.
Just from interest, there are some other algorithms
for doing matrix multiplication.
Is this only for just doing it normally?
So the question is that there are other algorithms
of doing matrix multiplication.
You mean like sub cubic algorithms?
So in general, that's--
the optimization, the algorithms that people
are going to explore for multiple matrix multiplications
are going to be much more about how you co-design
with the systems, rather than these more
asymptotic algorithms.
We're considering additional multiplication
in the same way is not possible to do division more efficiently
than multiplication.
Yeah, so I think the way the hardware is built,
the two are basically the same.
But yeah, intuitively it seems like I can do addition faster
than I do multiplication.
But the way the hardware is kind of the same.
So you can think about this MatMul
as B is the number of data points.
And D K is the number of parameters.
So remember x is B by D and w is D by K.
So another way to think about this formula
is that the number of FLOPs in order to do
a forward pass of this linear matrix
is actually 2 times the number of tokens or data points
times the number of parameters.
So it turns out that this actually
generalizes to transformers, which
if you remember the 6 times n times d formula,
we can see the shape of that forming.
So unfortunately these calculations
are not going to be very meaningful
because I'm doing this on CPU.
But I'll just walk through the code here.
So what we've done so far is measured FLOPs.
So this is independent of hardware.
It's just like the number of calculations
you need to do for your model.
So now the question is, how long does it actually
take on hardware? So one way to find out is you just time it.
So in this class, I think in the few lectures,
we're going to talk more about benchmarking.
But here's a little preview.
So in general, when you time especially on GPU,
you have to call cuda synchronize
to make sure that-- because the GPU is running asynchronously,
you want to make sure that you have this synchronization point.
And then you perform the operation.
And after operation, then you also
have to have the synchronization barrier.
If you omit this, you're going to find that wow,
your timings are really fast.
And that's because this is a non-blocking call.
It just returns. And often it's general good practice
to try this multiple times and take the average.
So the actual FLOPs per second is basically the number of FLOPs
you did times the time that you recorded on your hardware.
And so remember, there's also another number, which
is the GPU has a spec sheet.
Let's see if I can pull it up on this link.
I feel like maybe I have the wrong link.
I'll have to fix that after class.
--that it gives you some number of FLOPs,
which was 989 teraflops.
And so in general, the number of actual FLOPs per second
is going to be different from the promised FLOPs per second.
OK. Oops, sorry.
And the way to directly think about the discrepancy
is something called Model FLOPs Utilization, or MFU.
And the definition of MFU is the actual FLOPs
每秒除以承诺的FLOPs每秒。
这里忽略了通信
和其他开销。
所以你基本上取实际值除以承诺值。
所以一般来说，你很少能得到超过——
我的意思是，你——是的，你永远得不到超过
你被承诺的值。通常你会得到更少。
一般来说，如果现代模型的MFU能达到0.5，
你应该对自己相当满意了。
如果你只是做一个纯粹的矩阵乘法，
你可能能达到0.8甚至更高，
但你通常达不到那么高。
有时候如果你真的——某件事
真的出错了，你会得到
像0.1这样的结果，这意味着你应该做点什么。好。
所以每当你写模型时，你可以计算。
你现在知道如何通过结合
计算模型需要执行的逻辑FLOPs数量，
然后查看墙上时钟
时间并基本上相除来计算MFU。是的。
那边有问题吗？哦。[听不清]
是的。那么承诺——承诺的FLOPs数字是什么？
那在规格表中，它已经
除以2了，那个989的数字。
然后在此基础上，一般来说你只能得到其中的0.5
取决于你的计算。
[听不清]你得到50%的MFU？
是的，那么为什么你只得到50%的MFU？
实际上，这是个好问题。
我会在讨论内存瓶颈时再回来讲这个。
好。所以这里总结一下，矩阵乘法
通常主导了计算。这是设计使然。
而每秒的FLOPs数量取决于硬件。
所以更好的硬件带来更多的FLOPs
并且还取决于数据类型。
这意味着如果你查看规格表，
不同的数据类型会有不同的FLOPs。
如果你现在尝试使用float32，
它会非常非常慢，因为他们并没有真正
为此工作负载进行优化。
Whereas now bf16 or fp8 are going to be much faster.
And MFU-- now you know what MFU is.
It's the actual FLOPs divided by promised FLOPs.
All right. So to go back to the question of why is MFU 0.5.
And to understand that, I'm going
to have to introduce this idea of arithmetic intensity.
And the reason is that, well, it's not just
doing a bunch of MatMuls and then you're
done and looking at how long the MatMuls take.
This is my very cartoon version of what hardware looks like.
You have high bandwidth memory.
And then you have where the compute cores are,
the accelerator chips are. And then how do you compute?
Well, you have to send your inputs, your matrices--
the tensors are sitting down here--
from the memory to the accelerator.
You do the computation, and then you send it back.
So if you want to measure how long this takes,
this depends on two things.
One is the accelerator speed, which
is what we've talked about just now.
But the other thing that matters is the memory bandwidth
of your hardware, which we haven't talked about.
And if you look at the spec sheet,
we talked about how the FLOPs per second was 1979e12 divided
by 2.
And the bytes per second, which is the memory bandwidth,
this is 3.3 terabytes per second.
And remember why we were looking at memory,
how much things took to store.
It's most obviously that, well, if you
have a model that's too big it doesn't
fit in your memory, that's not going to be fun.
But also it turns out that memory--
you need to move this memory, which takes time.
So actually the size of how large things
actually influences speed as well. OK.
So I'm going to talk through some operations,
and I'm going to basically compute
how long things are going to take and introduce
这个算术强度的概念。
好，假设我有一个百万维的 bf16 向量。
然后我要对它计算一个 ReLU。
记住 ReLU 就是取 x
和 0 的逐元素最大值，作用于整个向量。
所以我计算两件事，一是
移动的字节数。所以我要读入 x——
把它复制到加速器里。
每一个都是 2
因为 bf16 是每个浮点数 2 字节，乘以 n 个浮点数。
所以是 2n。然后我要把 y 写回去。
所以又是 2n。好。
这就是需要移动的字节数。
那么做了多少 FLOPs？
每个元素，我只是拿它和零比较，
就这样。所以是 n 次比较。
那么现在看通信时间，
就是我需要移动的字节数除以
移动的速度。
这给出时间，是 1e-6 秒。
那计算时间呢？
就是 FLOPs 除以每秒 FLOPs。
所以是 1e-9。好。
还有一个重要的假设
我们通常试图保持，就是重叠通信
和计算。我们会在
更深入讨论 GPU 时多谈这个。
但这个想法是，在这种情况下
我们不会坐在这里等东西移动。
一旦它们到了，我们就开始计算，
然后把它们移回去。
所以这个移动以及计算
是同时发生的。
所以数学上，我们只是
假设总时间是两者的最大值，
因为我们假设可以完美地
重叠它们。
实践中，它不会完美重叠。
会有一些开销。
但这对现在来说足够了。好。
So the total time, as we see here, is 1e-6. OK.
So if you ask what is the bottleneck here?
So when the communication time is greater than the computation
time, then we call it the algorithm memory bound,
because you're spending most of your time just waiting
for bits to show up. And when the computation time is greater
than the communication time, that's
compute bound, because then you're
actually-- your bottleneck is actually doing the compute.
And so in this case, what is ReLU?
Rectified Linear Unit. Oh, sorry.
Is it memory bound or compute bound? Memory bound. Yeah.
And it's clear, because the compute is way less
than the communication.
So here's another way to see it.
And this is where I'm going to define the intensity.
So what is the intensity of an accelerator is essentially
how much work can the accelerator do per byte transferred.
And for any given accelerator based on the spec sheet,
you basically have the FLOPs per second divided
by the bytes per second.
So how much useful work can you do per byte
that's moved for each 100? That's 295.
So that means for every byte of--
you can do 295 floating point operations.
So that's an intuitive number to have in your head, about 300.
OK. So now the arithmetic intensity of algorithm
is how much actual work was done per byte for this workload.
And if you look at it for the ReLU computation,
it's FLOPs over bytes and it's actually-- so this is actually
a quarter, I guess, not half.
So the point is that it's very small, 0.25. OK.
So now we can talk about bottlenecks
through the language of intensity.
So something is memory bound if the arithmetic intensity is
smaller than the accelerator intensity
and compute bound if it's greater than accelerator intensity.
So these are equivalent. And if you look at the algebra, it's
basically you have two fractions.
And then you just multiply and divide to-- you
basically switch the terms around. OK.
So in this case, we're memory bound.
So in general, we're going to find ourselves in a situation
where we're memory bound because data movement is expensive.
And so if you can get higher arithmetic intensity,
that's good.
So 0.25, if you see that number, if someone tells you
arithmetic intensity is 0.25, you should say, oh,
this is really bad. Yeah.
What's some typical arithmetic intensity for some transformer
[INAUDIBLE]? Yeah, so we'll get to that. OK. All right. So OK.
So one way to think about increasing arithmetic intensity
is that let's just try to do more stuff per unit
of byte moved. So the GELU is another activation.
It looks like this, some formula that is more--
doesn't have zeros.
And if you do this calculation, the number of bytes are moved
back and forth is still 2n plus 2n.
And the FLOPs here it's about 20 FLOPs per elementwise scalar
operation, so it's 20n.
So the arithmetic intensity is, let's say, 5.
This is a crude estimate.
And in this case, are we memory bound or compute bound?
Memory bound.
Memory bound, because 5 is still smaller than 295, way smaller.
So even though GELU does a lot of work, more work than ReLU,
in the way that things are structured,
it's still memory bound.
Which means that if you were just computing ReLU and GELU,
you think that, well, GELU is so complicated,
it must be really expensive.
But actually it's exactly the same,
because that's not where the bottleneck is.
OK, so now let's look at some linear operations,
so dot product. So dot product, you have a vector x.
You have a vector w, size n, and you take the dot product.
So how many bytes are moved?
So you read x, which is 2n; read w, which is 2n;
and then you write y, which is a scalar, which is 2.
And the number of FLOPs is you do the n multiplications
and n minus 1 additions. So that's 2n minus 1. OK.
So what's the arithmetic intensity?
Oh, for this one, it's about half, which is also pretty bad.
Which means that-- hopefully you get
the idea-- it's memory bound.
So what about a matrix-vector product?
So I have this x is a vector. w is an n by n matrix.
And you form this product.
How many of you think this will be compute bound?
How many of you think memory bound? OK. So let's see.
So I'm going to read x, which is 2n; read w,
which is 2n squared; and write y, which is 2n.
And then the number of FLOPs is basically
you're doing n dot products.
So that's n times the cost of doing a dot product.
And the arithmetic intensity is barely, barely higher.
So this is also memory bound. OK.
So now let's talk about matrix multiplication.
So this is where things get interesting.
So I have an n by m matrix, another m by n matrix.
And I multiply them.
And the number of bytes that were moved was 2n squared plus
2n squared.
And then I have to write 2n squared bytes back to y.
And the number of FLOPs here is n squared dot products.
And then what's arithmetic intensity? It's 300. Whew.
OK, so 340. And in general, it's roughly n over 3.
And intuitively this makes sense because you're
sending n squared things, but you're computing n cubed things.
So the number of things you're computing over
the number of things you're sending is order n.
And this gets better the larger you make the matrices.
So in general, this is why when you hear people talk about, oh,
we need to make large batch sizes or have large matrices,
it's exactly this.
If you're under the arithmetic intensity, making things smaller
doesn't actually speed things up. It's all the same.
Whereas if you get to a point where you're over this,
then you're actually saturating your GPUs. OK.
So finally, this is compute bound. OK.
So as long as we have large matrices,
we're actually pretty good.
We're in a compute bound saturating the accelerator.
And the question earlier about what about transformers?
Well, it turns out we'll see in both your assignment,
but also in the next lecture that transformers
are essentially big matrix multiplications with some things
sprinkled in between.
So that's good news from arithmetic intensity.
And this is, by design, transformer
is designed in a certain way to have high arithmetic intensity.
And one comment here, just to foreshadow
the inference lecture, is that matrix vector products
is essentially what goes on when you're
doing transformer inference.
Because inference, you're generating one token at a time.
And so you only get to-- it's like a vector
that you're trying to dot product with a matrix.
And that's as we saw with memory bound.
Whereas at training time, you get this whole sequence
and you're processing all at once. OK.
So note also that the intensity depends on the precision.
So by default everything we're doing here is fp16.
OK. So also to tie it to the other question about MFU,
and the reason you might be getting low MFU is
that while you might be doing-- so MFU is a promise FLOPs--
sorry, actual over promise.
So if you have really large memory bottlenecks,
then you're not actually going to get very good throughput,
even though you--
the promise is if you didn't have memory bottlenecks,
you were just like going through and doing all the computations
of your model.
OK. Final thing on arithmetic intensity roofline plots.
So there's a nice way to-- yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] generally speaking, these models
tend to be memory bound, as they say for most of the computation.
But yet the accelerators are 50% is not as good.
And maybe you get 70, maybe you get 80 that's really good,
meaning that the accelerator is outsized
compared to memory bandwidth. Why is it like that?
Why do these accelerators—
are just big while they're just idling or waiting for memory?
So the question is, could you design maybe accelerators that
had better characteristics? Yeah.
Maybe when we talk about GPUs and understand
a bit more how they work, we can talk about why this is.
But if you have an answer, you should tell Jensen.
And maybe you can design a better hardware.
OK, so let's visualize the relationship between arithmetic
intensity and performance.
So this plot basically plots the arithmetic intensity
on the x-axis.
So every slice here corresponds to a particular, let's say,
algorithm. And then we have these lines here.
And each of these lines corresponds to, let's say,
a particular accelerator. Maybe H100 or B200 or so.
And so what this shows is— and then on the y-axis
is the FLOPs per second that are realized.
So if your algorithm has low arithmetic intensity, like, ReLU
or dot products, you're going to be
over here, which means that the FLOPs per second realized
is going to be not as high as your peak accelerator.
And as you increase the memory arithmetic intensity,
that's going to— things are going to be better.
You're going to be able to saturate your hardware up
until a certain point.
And after a certain point your compute bound.
And obviously you can't exceed the peak FLOPs.
All right. So let's go on here. OK.
So now I'm going to go back and talk about memory
and compute for the operations that we need in training.
So far we've done tensor operations, basically MatMuls.
And we saw basically how much memory it took
and how much compute it took and the interaction between them.
So now let's actually think about what it takes to train.
So here is our running example here.
Actually it's not a linear network, just a deep network.
So I'm going to consider a case where I have an input, which
is a B by D input, and a number of layers
where each layer is a D by D MatMul.
And then that produces some set of preactivations
and then element-wise ReLU that produces some activations
of the first layer.
And then this is repeated again and again.
And the output is just going to be the same size.
So the deep network, I mean, just
to see what it looks like in PyTorch,
just so it's basically a set of blocks.
Each block has a weight vector—
sorry, a weight matrix associated with it.
And so when you, the number of parameters
here is D squared times the number of layers L.
And when you run the model on the batch of data, what we're
doing is we're going through the layers, and each layer
we basically apply the linear transformation and then
a pointwise ReLU activation.
And then we do that for all the layers.
So this is hopefully straightforward, very simple model. OK.
So now let's talk about gradients.
So let's use actually an even simpler example.
So this is just a simple linear model regression.
So we have a vector 1, 2, 3, a weight vector 1, 1, 1.
And we take the dot product, and we form this MSE loss. OK.
And what happens when we take the—do the backward pass is
that each of the variables involved in this computation
graph has a gradient that is either set or not set.
So the w.grad gets set to 1, 2, 3.
So this is just basic mechanics of PyTorch.
I think it should be familiar to all of you.
So now the question is, how much compute does gradients take?
OK. So let's count FLOPs for computing gradients.
So let's take a simplified model where
you have an x, which is BID and times w1 matrix.
We're going to ignore this ReLU for now
just for simplicity times w2, which is the same D by D—
same shape D by D matrix. OK.
I'm going to use einsum here for reasons that will become clear.
So the first thing you do in this linear network
is you take x and you take w1. x is batch by input dimension.
w1 is as in by out, and you get a batch by out.
And h2 takes h1 and w2, and it's the same story.
These are just MatMuls.
And then you form a loss.
I'm just sending it to some arbitrary
to get a number out. OK. So what happens in the backward pass,
I'm going to call these retain gradients
for debugging purposes, which you'll see later.
You take the backward pass on the loss.
And the question is, how much work
did that-- how many floating point operations was that?
So let's zoom in on one layer.
Let's focus on the second layer here, so this layer.
And so the second layer takes h1 and just multiplies it
by a matrix w2 to get h2. And that's it.
So if you look at the FLOPs in the forward pass,
this is just a MatMul. And we just take the three dimensions,
and we multiply them together and bf16. That's 2 bytes.
Sorry, that's irrelevant.
This is just 2 because it's an addition and a multiplication.
So in the backward pass, what does this look like?
So in the backward pass, if you remember your chain
rule and your backprop algorithm,
you have to compute two things.
You have to compute the backward message,
the gradient of the loss with respect to your input.
And you also have to compute the gradient with respect
to your parameters. And what do those gradients look like?
This is just by the definition of these--
I guess this is just the chain rule here written
in einsum notation.
You take the d loss d h2, which is h2 grad.
That's a batch by Alt matrix, and you multiply it
by w2, which is in by out.
And then that gives you h1 grad, which is d loss d h1 and which
is batch n.
So I always get this confused whenever if you see--
learn calculus, there's like, one of them has a transpose,
and I forget which order to put them in.
And einsum I think makes it very clear,
because you can remember even just looking at the scalar case
that it has to look like h1.grad is h2.grad times w2.
And the only question is, how do you index things?
And you index things by basically
looking at the shape of these—and the named dimensions.
And in this case, it's just a matrix multiplication
where you are summing over the output dimension.
And when you do that, we can check that.
So h1.grad was the thing that was computed by loss.backward.
And this is actually indeed the same thing
that I wrote out here just as a sanity check.
So the other thing you have to compute
is w, the gradient with respect to the parameters.
And that's d loss d h2 times h1.
So it's the same kind of backward message that's
coming back but multiplying with the other thing
that you're not taking the gradient with respect to.
And you just write out the dimensions.
And in this case, you're summing over the batch dimension.
But the nice thing is that if you just look at this,
we know how expensive this is.
The number of FLOPs is essentially the product
of all the dimensions.
It doesn't matter which ones you're batching or not.
It's basically you enumerate over the i, j, k, and you
aggregate. The way that you aggregate is different,
but the FLOPs is the same. OK.
So notice that the backward pass is exactly twice as
expensive as the forward pass.
And this is because you have to take—
compute two gradients, one with respect
to the parameters for each parameter,
and then one with respect to the input,
the other thing that's not the parameter. Maybe I'll pause.
Any questions about that?
OK. So now that was just for w2.
And you just need to apply this to all the parameters
in the network.
And you put it all together, you will see that for this network,
the forward pass is 2 times the number
of data points, which is b times the number of parameters FLOPs.
And the backward pass is twice of that,
which is 4 times the number of data points times the number
of parameters FLOPs.
And so the grand total is 2 plus 4 is 6, and 6 times the number
of data points and parameters.
So this is where the 6 nd comes from that you might
have seen in various places.
It's just by counting forward and backward.
So we did this for just these deep networks.
But it turns out that this is actually
a good approximation for transformers
as well—as long as the context length isn't too large.
If the context length is too large,
then you get the context length squared,
and that's more FLOPs that isn't in this kind of accounting.
OK. So let's talk a bit about—so now we have gradients.
Now we have to—the other piece when
you do training is we have to do optimization.
So here's our deep network.
Just so that I'm not just giving you what's in assignment 1,
I'm going to use the AdaGrad optimizer, which
this is from—this is from 2011. This predates Adam.
It's where you can think about it as somewhere
in between SGD and Adam.
And basically it's SGD where you look at the second moments
of the gradient.
Momentum is where you look at the first moment gradients.
And Adam is where you combine the two of them.
I'm not going to have time to go into the optimizer details here,
since we're focusing mostly on the usage.
So we can define an optimizer.
And when you compute the gradients
and you compute the gradients and then
when you take an optimizer step, if you're
defining a new optimizer, so in assignment 1,
you're going to implement Adam.
For each of the parameter groups which are,
in this case w1 or w2, we look at—
there's something called optimizer state, which
是存储的-- 优化器
运行时使用的。我们在 AdaGrad 中计算的是
某种-- 是梯度平方，平方
梯度之和。
所以这里我们从优化器状态中获取它。
我们用当前梯度更新它，
然后把它存回去。然后在你更新 g2 之后，
再更新参数。
所以在 AdaGrad 中，基本上
除以梯度平方平均值的平方根，或者说
梯度平方之和。好，那我们来看。
所以其实我可能要跳过训练循环。
等等，
我觉得我跳过了某些本不想跳过的内容。好。
所以那是优化器状态，现在我们来看
优化器使用了多少内存。
或者一般来说内存使用量是多少？
那么对于这个网络中的参数，
每 L 层有 D 平方个参数。
如果我们用 fp16 存储，每个参数占 2 字节。
所以这就是参数数量。
激活--这是 2 乘以--
这是 bf16 的批次大小乘以 D 乘以层数。
每一层都有激活。
还有梯度，基本上就是
所有参数的一份副本。这也是 bf16。
而优化器状态对于每个--
其实这里应该是--
我觉得这里应该是--抱歉，我来修正一下。
这是个笔误。
这里应该是参数数量，不是参数
内存。这里应该是参数数量，
所以是参数数量乘以 2，然后这里
是 4 乘以参数数量。
原因是，
习惯上用 fp32 存储优化器状态以保证稳定性。
显然人们尝试过用 bf16。
结果就是，你在做平方，
然后对多步求平均，这并不--
它不太稳定。
而对于 AdaGrad，这里每参数占 4 个字节，
用于存储优化器状态。
Adam 会存储一阶矩和二阶
矩，所以是 8 个字节。
所以如果想想优化器
状态实际上占了很大一部分内存。
有一点需要注意，内存有两个用途。
一是你必须把这些东西存储在 HBM 中。
但另一点是它
必须被传输到加速器上。
一般来说，优化器状态
并不是计算瓶颈。
所以这里的内存大小
对速度性能并不是很重要，
但它意味着你无法在内存中容纳大模型。
好，那么总结一下，正如我们提到的，
这里的参数量是 D 乘以 D 乘以 L，
而 FLOPs 数量是 D 乘以 token 数
或数据点数乘以参数量。
所以对于 transformer 来说，这会
稍微复杂一些。
但你会在作业 1 中做这个。
你会更仔细地完成它。好。
我会跳过训练循环。
这只是一个总体回顾。
在结束之前，我想快速讲两点。
一是正如我们所见，内存确实有重要影响，
既影响存储大模型的能力，
有时也影响你的速度。
所以一般来说，你希望减少内存使用。
人们通常会做两件事。
一是梯度累积。
一般来说，你希望使用足够大的批次大小
以提升稳定性，
直到达到临界批次大小，
Tatsu 稍后会讲到这一点。
正如我们所见，激活内存随批次大小增长。
所以在某些时候你可能会内存不足，
如果你的批次大小太大。
所以梯度累积就是说，你计算。
You have these micro batches, and you compute the gradient
on the micro batches.
And then you just accumulate the gradients.
You don't zero out the gradients.
And every batch size over microbatch size
steps, you update the parameters and zero out the gradients.
OK, so this is actually a very simple code change which
allows you to save on compute.
So the other thing I'll quickly mention
is activation checkpointing.
So in training, we need to store in general the activations
of all the layers.
This is done by default. Actually, interestingly,
for inference we don't need to compute the gradient,
so we only need to store the current layer's activations.
But for training, the memory usage is B times D times 2 times
L. And the question is, can you reduce this?
So activation checkpointing, also known
as gradient checkpointing or rematerialization-- the key idea
here is that in the forward pass,
you just keep activations for only a subset of the layers.
And in the backward pass, you recompute the missing
activations from the last checkpoint.
That's why it's called checkpointing.
And this is a general trick that you see in systems
which is trading off.
If you want to reduce memory, you can just recompute things.
So here we're going to define this to operationalize this.
This is actually fairly easy. Actually, I didn't--
OK, maybe I didn't see the--
OK, so basically what you do here
is you have the same model, except for you just add Torch
utils at checkpoint on a layer.
So that means do this computation,
but don't store any of the intermediate activations.
Only store what is needed.
So this means that if you store all the activations, remember
in your deep network, you have the thing that's
pre the ReLU and the thing that's after the ReLU right.
So that's a lot of storage.
And instead if you do activation checkpointing on those blocks
where each block has a linear and ReLU,
you don't store the pre ReLU, and you save basically half.
You can get away with half the memory.
And then when you're doing the backward pass, you need g3,
but you can compute g3 easily from h2. OK.
You can go further than this.
You can say, well, I can store all the layers,
but in the extreme case, I can just store no layers.
And so that will be maximally memory efficient.
The only thing is that the compute is going to be L squared.
Because for every one of these layers,
you have to start from the beginning.
And maybe a sweet spot is if you store the checkpoints
at square root L layers, that means your activation memory is
square root of L, and your recomputation overhead
is also square root of L. So that's balanced. OK.
So to summarize this lecture, everything
is operating on tensors-- parameters, gradients,
activations, optimization states, data.
We introduced this einops, which hopefully you guys
can embrace as a way to think about tensor operations.
6 times number of data points times number of parameters
is a formula which now we have demystified
as the number of FLOPs per--for training step.
And actually if this is training step, this should be batch size.
And then we talked about arithmetic intensity
and roofline analysis, which allows
us to diagnose whether a computation is
memory bound or compute bound.
Matrix multiplications are compute bound.
Basically everything else is memory bound.
And then finally, gradient accumulation, activation,
checkpointing are ways to reduce the memory.
And by reducing the memory, that allows
you to use bigger batch sizes. OK.
So that's it for today's lecture.
So next week, Tatsu will talk about architectures.